all right well you asked for it let's
practice some multiple choice questions
for apush this is an official practice
exam published by the college board and
if you want to follow along you can
either look at it on the screen or you
can download it at the link in the
description and all these questions i'm
not going to take the time to read them
out so pause it when you see it on the
screen and read it for yourself do the
questions for yourself because only in
that way will you really start to get
better okay here's the first stimulus so
go ahead and pause it and read it now
the first thing you should do with any
stimulus bar none is start with the
attribution here we see it's from the
seneca falls convention the declaration
of sentiments and resolutions 1848. now
here's the thing if you know what the
declaration of sentiments is and you
should because mentioned in the ced and
you know the date 1848 you could
actually answer these questions that
follow without even reading the stimulus
now i don't exactly recommend that but
i'm just telling you that if you know
what the attribution is then you know a
lot already without even reading the
stimulus and that is going to save you
some time so the second thing you need
to do is quickly read through the
stimulus and mark up the important parts
here i'm going to mark the elective
franchise which she has no voice of the
elected franchise again and all right in
property this little excerpt is all
about how women have been denied certain
rights especially in this case the
elective franchise which is to say the
right to vote in american society and
that level of analysis is all i need to
know i don't need to go into depth here
i just need to understand the main gym
okay now here's the first question the
ideas expressed in the excerpt most
directly challenge the prevailing ideal
in the early 19th century that now
before i go any further i want to mark
up the question itself i want to
underline directly challenged so that
means one of these answers is going to
challenge what the declaration of
sentiments and resolutions is saying and
i need to find out which one that is
would be a that women should enjoy full
and equal rights with men now that's
tricky because that is what this
document is saying that women should
have full and equal rights with men but
notice what the question says which of
these directly challenges what the
document is saying so it can't be a
because a is agreeing with what the
document is saying is it c the ability
of women to earn wages was a positive
development again this one is tricky
because obviously the authors of the
declaration would agree that women
earning wages is a positive development
but that is not challenging what she is
saying what they are saying in this
document or would it be d women should
educate their children about the rights
and responsibilities of citizenship now
that of course is something that occurs
in american history but that is outside
the time period what we're talking about
here is the republican motherhood the
idea that women should raise up their
sons to be good citizens but that's
really a post-american revolution
phenomenon so that is not the answer the
answer is b women should focus on the
home and domestic sphere the declaration
of sentiments is directly challenging
the idea that women should stay home and
make their husbands sandwiches okay next
question which of the following
developments in the second half of the
19th century i'm always going to
underline the time periods that they
give me because i need to focus there
and make sure that i'm answering within
that time period which of the following
developments best represents the
continuation of the ideas expressed in
the declaration i'm also always going to
underline the historical thinking skill
that they're asking me to perform so in
this case it is continuity which of
these ideas is continuing later in the
19th century does it be women's support
for the social gospel i mean yes women
did support the social gospel but again
that is outside the time period because
that's the first half of the 20th
century was it c support for outlawing
the production and sale of alcohol i
mean that again is tricky because women
did participate in the temperance
movement but again that is outside the
time period the emphasis for the
temperance movement is in the beginning
of the 20th century not the last half of
the 19th century or is it d a movement
focused on religious revivals and
personal conversions that's another one
that's outside the time period it's
asking me about the second half of the
19th century and the religious revivals
that you learned about the first great
awakening and second great awakening all
happened before that so the answer is a
the formation of voluntary organizations
and reform efforts there were a lot of
reform movements cropping up in the
second half of the 19th century and
women were deeply involved in those
primarily because they could not vote
and so this was the way that they
affected change okay now let's move to
another set of questions and this set of
questions is attached to a different
kind of stimulus namely a visual
stimulus in this case a graph so when
i'm getting oriented to a stimulus like
this there are a couple of things i want
to do first now the first thing you're
going to be tempted to do is start
looking at this line and trying to
interpret what it means but that's not
the first thing you do the first thing
you do is you look at the title of the
graph this line is going to indicate the
number of immigrants coming to the
united states between 1820 and 1860. so
before i even look at any questions the
only thing i really need to pay
attention to is the fact that in this
period right here there seems to be a
huge upsurge in immigrants that's enough
to look at the first question which of
the following was a significant cause
okay i'm going to underline that because
that's the historical thinking skill
what was the significant cause of the
trend from 1843 to 1854 shown in the
ground okay now at this point you're
going to be under pressure so make sure
you mark those dates on the graph so
that you know what you're talking about
here's 1843 here's 1854. okay between
those years why are so many immigrants
coming to america is it the act of
encouragement of migration by the united
states government you know anything
about united states history you know
that is rarely if ever the case this is
incentives offered by united states
companies looking to hire skilled
migrants here i just want to point out
that it says skilled migrants that can't
be right because most of the immigrants
coming into work were unskilled laborers
who worked in factories so that can't be
right is it the adoption of free trade
policies by european governments now
ultimately that's outside the time
period that's going to happen later
europe is still at this point still
hanging on to the remnants of
mercantilism they are in transition but
the transition has not completed yet the
answer is b economic and political
difficulties in germany and ireland
remember that germans were coming over
because of the failed revolution of 1848
and the irish were coming over because
of the irish potato famine so that's why
you get all these immigrants coming over
during this period okay next question
which of the following was a direct
effect of the trend in immigration after
1845 shown in the graph okay now this is
kind of the opposite of the previous
question the other question asked what
caused all of this now what are the
effects of all of this is it a an
increase in sectional tensions in almost
every case when we're in this time
period when we talk about sectional
tensions we're talking about the tension
of slavery between the north and the
south so it definitely can't be that was
it be did all these immigrants coming in
affect a major economic downturn here
they might be talking about the panic of
1837 in the panic of 1857 but in either
case neither of those are true because
immigrants actually helped the economy
didn't hurt it now the tricky one is d
the collapse of the second party system
this did happen right about the same
time but that happened because of the
tension in the north and the south over
slavery not because of immigration so
the answer is c an upsurge in nativist
sentiment remember that nativism was a
reaction against immigrants and so
that's clearly the answer here okay the
next question the main trend shown in
the graph was most directly associated
all right stop for a second when you see
language like that something that most
directly caused something else or
something most directly associated with
something else that should be an alarm
bell in your head that says every answer
that i'm about to see is actually
correct factually they're just asking me
which one has the tightest association
so you got to be careful okay so the
main trend shown on the graph was most
directly associated with which of the
following processes occurring in the
united states at the time is today the
convergence of european and american
cultures well no during this time
america is actually trying to
distinguish itself culturally from
europe does it see the displacement of
american indians from the southeast now
that's also outside of this time period
that happened before the time period
we're looking at here but also the
displacement of american indians
actually has nothing to do with
immigration so we're trying to find out
what is most directly associated it
can't be this is it d the resurgence of
evangelical protestantism again that's
outside the time period of the question
we're talking about the second great
awakening here and so that can't be
remember we're trying to make an
association between the spike in
immigration and something else that's
going on that encourages that
immigration so the answer is b the
emergence of an industrialized economy
with all the new industrial jobs opening
up that created an incentive for
immigrants to come and find work okay so
let me summarize the tips of what we've
learned through this exercise number one
make sure you are studying in the
context of your time periods think about
how many of these wrong answers were
wrong because they were outside the time
period that we were considering number
two always read the attribution of the
stimulus first some cases you could
answer the questions just by reading the
attribution third make sure you are
marking up the question because when
you're under pressure you are dumber
than you think and that is going to help
you and fourth just remember in order to
get yourself into the range of a passing
score you only need to get about 55-ish
percent correct on the multiple choice
and then you know you have to go on and
do well on the writing sections but
don't stress too much okay then multiple
choice is only one section on your exam
here are some videos that are going to
help you with the writing section i hope
that helped and i'll see you around
heimler out